{
  "reference_number": "12185",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "We need climate action and ambitious targets as soon as possible. Less mucking around, more forcing a quick transition to a low\n carbon economy."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "As a greenhouse gase, methane is much more powerful than carbon dioxide, even though methane is short lived. Don't let\n\n Federated Farmers keep repeating that methane is a short lived gas when they don't also say it is a powerful greenhouse gas.\n Methane is very bad in the atmosphere, so we need net zero emissions of it also, by 2050 or sooner."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We need to clean up our own act and lead the way. Good if we can also help other countries reduce their emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "We should allow the target to be revised ONLY if the target becomes more ambitious. Climate change is a serious and urgent threat\n to the whole planet."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes if it forces action to be taken sooner rather than put off until later."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Government absolutely needs to take strong urgent action to reduce emissions. It can't be allowed to get out of it by saying 'it's\n too hard right now.'"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission should not take economic and fiscal circumstances into account when advising on setting\nbudgets. Urgent and necessary action on climate change has been delayed for too long for fear of hurting the economy or fiscal\n\ncircumstances. This has meant worse climate change will come and hurt our economy more than if we had reduced emissions\nearlier. Climate change is a huge long term problem which requires ignoring short term economic and fiscal circumstances."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The fossil fuel industry needs to be ignored when setting plans to meet budgets as their industry is killing our planet."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": "Governments can ignore good advice. ETS should be set with the goal of drasticly reducing carbon emissions firmly in sight."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Keep the main thing as the main thing. Don't distract or dilute the bill's ability to reduce carbon emissions by trying to get it to do\nother things as well. Having said that, adaptation should be nationally coordinated."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
